# Alexandra Carolina Marcos Quispe

alexandra.marcos@pucp.edu.pe | (+51) 914073042 Github: https://github.com/alexandramarcos1896 LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexandra-carolina-marcos

## PERSONAL PROFILE

A committed and proactive economist with a strong passion for pursuing a PhD in Management, Science and Engineering. A current project manager and research assistant motivated to study the implementation of algorithms in addressing economic and social challenges, specifically interested in the Computational Social Science area. Passion for econometrics which increased after earning the highest mark in the Applied Econometrics course and completing a research internship at the Central Bank of Peru. Experienced in machine learning models in justice agencies, as well as presenting at a conference and assisting in the development of research papers.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú (PUCP)

Lima, Peru

B.A. Economics

Mar 2020

Graduated First in Class and top 5% in the program history (since 1970).

GPA: 15.24/20.00

• Relevant Coursework: Microeconomics 1, Microeconomics 2, Macroeconomics 1, Macroeconomics 2, Applied Econometrics, Advanced Econometrics: Time Series and Intermediate Econometrics.

#### Universidad de los Andes

Bogota, Colombia

**Exchanges Studies** 

Jan - Jun 2018

Fully funded by the Economics Department and the Alianza del Pacífico Scholarship.

GPA: 4.33/5.00

• Relevant Coursework: Matlab workshop, Development Policies Seminar through the ELCA Database, and Social Project Evaluation Seminar.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant Remote

Msc. Alexander Quispe

Oct - Nov 2021

- Contributed to the development of a machine learning handbook with Python and R applications.
- Participated in the professor's Machine Learning course, acquiring knowledge of ML models and their applications.

Research Assistant Remote

Prof. Alisha Holland, Harvard University

Nov 2020 - Jun 2021

- Structured data using R on Peruvian public works projects and analyzed discontinuities in project creation following the establishment of the National Public Investment System (SNIP).
- Built a Twitter scraper using Python to collect presidential and regional candidates' tweets from three electoral processes and countries: Peru, Colombia and Ecuador.
- Developed a label classifier using Python to identify four categories: public work projects, welfare, job creation, and economic growth.

Research Assistant

Msc. Victor Gamarra

Oct - Dec 2020

• Assisted in the development of a working paper for the Peruvian National Council for Science, Technology, and Technological Innovation (CONCYTEC). It explores how R&D+I influences economic growth and identifies the sectors that contribute the most to it.

• Defined the methodological framework, systematized the literature review, and estimated key indicators of R&D+I using survey data from Peru and Chile.

Research Assistant Remote

Phd. Jose Incio, University of Pittsburgh

Jun - Oct 2020

- Built a Twitter scraper in Python to collect tweets mentioning government representatives and structured the output for a sentiment analysis.
- Estimated the COVID-19 virus spread rate using a SIRD model based on the methodology of Jesús Fernández-Villaverde and Charles I. Jones (2022).
- Collaborated on the construction of a COVID-19 library using R that systematized and simplified the cleaning process of Peruvian data.

Research Assistant

Lima, Peru

Prof. Marco Vega, The Central Reserve Bank of Peru (BCRP)

May - Jul 2020

- Estimated the COVID-19 death toll in Peru using a Poisson regression model based on the methodology of Weinberger et al. (2020), with the model coded appropriately in R.
- Forecasted the weekly evolution of the COVID-19 pandemic at the regional level and identified the most affected regions using the methodology of Weinberger et al. (2020), with the model coded efficiently in R.
- Developed a scraper in Python to collect financial data on public works projects in Peru.

Research Intern

Lima, Peru

The Central Reserve Bank of Peru (BCRP)

Oct 2018 - Set 2019

- Conducted research on the response of online prices in response to exchange rate fluctuations in retail stores, with the analysis coded in R.
- Presented the findings at the National Economist Conference to a specialized audience.
- Developed a scraper in R to collect news from Peruvian analytical and opinion newspapers.
- Conducted research on the impact of BCRP communication on market expectations by applying Structural Topic Modeling (STM) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to BCRP-related news and Inflation Reports.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Senior Project Manager - Consultancy

Remote

Columbia University in the City of New York

May 2023 - Present

- Planned the entire project's activities, involving five decision-making algorithms, using the agile methodology.
- Directed a team of six professionals to implement five decision-making algorithms to improve the triage and evaluation of whistleblower complaints.
- Mitigated the CGR representatives' mistrust of adopting algorithms in their workflow by explaining the variables behind each model and reviewing the predictions of randomly selected cases.

Senior Data Scientist Remote

Auditor General of the Peruvian Government (CGR)

Aug 2022 - Apr 2023

- Collaborated in the approach of the algorithm that prioritises the complaints of CGR's whistleblower system.
- Elaborated the architecture design of the web service, where algorithms predict and give real-time recommendations to the officials.
- Contributed in and automated the cleaning process of the whistleblower system's database using SQL SIS, reducing data processing time by 80%.
- Contributed to the development of a Python library for feature engineering the whistleblower database, reducing processing time by 50% and improving notebook readability.
- Created six machine learning algorithms to predict the likelihood being admitted for further evaluation using text embedding and readability indexes from the complaint descriptions.

## Senior Pricing Analyst

Scotiabank Peru Jan - Jun 2022

- Supported the project "Pricing Avanzado" in the creation of the mock-up solution.
- Created dashboards of disbursements and prices for retail products in PowerBi and Excel.
- Analyzed the daily evolution of disbursements and prices to alert of any potential drop in monthly sales.

## Programming Assistant of Public Budget

Lima, Peru

Lima, Peru

Ministry of Economics and Finances of Peru (MEF)

Dec 2021 - Dec 2022

- Automated historical revenue data cleaning process of public entities at the national, regional, and district levels from 2010 to 2020.
- Forecasted the revenue of public entities for the period 2022-2024, coded proficiently in R.
- Contributed to the development of public budget "Programación Multianual de Presupuesto 2022-2024".

#### AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

## Excellence Award 2019-II. Faculty of Social Sciences

Apr 2021

Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú (PUCP)

Awarded to the undergraduate student with the highest GPA in the major.

## Alianza del Pacifico Scholarship

Jan 2018

Awarded a full scholarship to pursue an academic exchange program in Colombia.

## LEADERSHIPS AND ACTIVITIES

MakerLab Lima, Peru

Mentor and Member

May - Dec 2023

- Mentor, Innova & Business Fest Hackathon Mibanco PUCP: "Disruption in Liabilities"
- Mentor, Social Sciences Innovation Challenge PUCP: "Combating Local Economic Corruption through New Technologies"
- Mentor, Second Environmental Innovation Challenge: "Sustainable Campus PUCP"

AIESEC Lima, Peru

OGX Member of the PUCP Local Committee.

Jun - Oct 2017

• Communicated the importance of volunteering and internships to undergraduate students and how these challenging experiences impact their personal and professional development.

#### Peruvian Economic Association (APE)

Lima, Peru

Annual Conference of the Peruvian Economic Association

Aug 2016

• Supported event logistics and addressed attendee inquiries.

## RELEVANT SKILLS

## **Technical**

- Proficient in R, Python, C, Matlab, JavaScript, SQL (PostgreSQL, SQL Server), and Stata.
- Experienced with GitHub and GitHub Actions and built web technologies with HTML, CSS, Flask, React, and Django.
- Developed with Linux, Ubuntu, and PowerShell and used tools such as Docker and Postman.

#### Language

Spanish (Native) and English (Proficient)

## CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

"Exchange Rate Pass-through of Online Prices", The Central Reserve Bank of Peru (BCRP), Universidad del Pacífico, October 2019.